Rachit Mittal

Data Analyst Intern | +91-7065614647 | rachitmittal428@gmail.com

linkedin.com/in/rachitmittal1994 | kaggle.com/rachitmittal1994

SUMMARY

A Data enthusiast with 2 years of experience in Data Analytics and Consulting, supporting Marketing and Sales business units. Skillful in identifying data issues and monitoring various metrics along with the expertise in building and deploying Machine Learning models.

SKILLS

Supervised Machine Learning: Data Engineering, Feature Engineering, Decision Trees, Random Forest, Naïve Bayes, SVM, Artificial Neural Networks, NLP, K- Nearest Neighbors

Unsupervised Machine Learning: PCA, Clustering, K-Means Clustering

Predictive Analytics: Time-Series Analysis, Forecasting, Regression

Statistical Methods: Univariate Analysis, Bi-Variate Analysis, Sampling, Hypothesis Testing

Programming Languages: Python, R, Basic VBA

Data Reporting Tool: Tableau

EXPERIENCE

Action Tesa, New Delhi> - Data Analyst Intern

January 2021 - PRESENT

- Identified, analyzed and interpreted trends and patterns in the data. Determining the seasonality in sales of various products and branches and calculating the future sales with 90% accuracy.
- Determining the **future potential markets** for the for the **seeding of the major products** of the company, and to **open new Dealers/ Distributors** to improve Dealer/Distributor network.

Mahindra & Mahindra Ltd., Noida – Management Trainee

June 2019 - December 2020

- Analyzed the trends of commercial vehicle industry of India and building **quarter-wise trend** charts for sales forecasting.
- Conducted application-wise research to improve sales/ demand forecasting and planning
 resulting in the better reach of the target audience bringing in the revenue of ₹ 11 crores for
 the company.
- Explored the various hubs/ districts of the given territory and identify the potential markets and conducted various BTL activities that resulted in ₹ 15 lakhs revenue for the dealer and ₹ 18 lakhs revenue for the company.
- Streamlined the process of customer acquisition and building a model to identify the customer churn rate with the accuracy of 80%.
- Improved the **market share of the company** from 3.23% in FY-19 to 4.56% in FY-20 in the given territory.

PROJECTS

Wine Sales Forecasting

- o Analyzed historical monthly sales data of a company. Created multiple forecast models for two different products and recommended the optimum forecasting model to predict monthly sales for the next 12 months along with appropriate lower and upper confidence limits.
- o Tools Used: Exploratory Data Analysis for Time Series Data, Exponential Smoothing Models, ARIMA/SARIMA Models, Moving Average Models

Exit Polls and Text Analytics

- o Generated a model to create an exit poll that will help in predicting overall win and seats covered by the particular party and analysis of the speeches of former US presidents.
- Tools Used: NLP, EDA, KNN, Naïve Bayes, Boosting, Bagging

• Gems and Holiday Package Prediction

- Created the model to predict the price of the gems on multiple variables to help companyto maximize the profits. Also, designed a model to predict if the customer will purchase the holiday package to target relevant customer base.
- o Tools Used: Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, Linear Discriminant Analysis

• Bank Customer Segmentation and Insurance Claim

- Developed a customer segmentation model to help company provide promotional offers to its customer. Along with reducing the tour insurance claims and maximizing the profit for the company.
- Tools Used: Random Forest, Decision Trees, ANN

ACHIEVEMENTS or AWARDS

- Shinkansen Travel Experience Hackathon: Predicted whether a passenger was delighted considering his/her overall travel experience of traveling in Shinkansen with 95.12% Accuracy.
- Won ₹ 500 Amazon Voucher for winning the McDonald's Competition.

EDUCATION

Great Lakes Learnings and Texas McCombs University

(2020-Pursuing)

PGP- Data Science and Business Analytics.

Birla Institute of Management Technology, Greater Noida

(2017-2019)

PGDM International Business Marketing.

Secured a CGPA of 7.55.

Bharati Vidyapeeth College of Engineering, New Delhi

(2012-2016)

BTech Instrumentation & Control Engineering.

• Graduated with 74.3%.